RG 028:002, Commission on the Reorganization of State Departments, 1935-1937
Connecticut State Library
Commission on the Reorganization of State Departments records
1935-1937
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Commission on the Reogranization of State Departments
11 cubic feet
The Commission made recommendations and proposed legislation to streamline State government that at the time consisted of 160 agencies among the three branches.
RG028_002
Multiple
Historical Note
The Commission on the Reorganization of State Departments was established pursuant to Special Act No. 242 of 1935, which provided for appointment by the Governor, with the advice and consent of the General Assembly, of a five-member commission to make studies and prepare recommendations and proposed legislation. Governor Wilbur Cross called the first meeting in his office on June 21, 1935, at which Col. Thomas Hewes was elected chairman. Benjamin P. Whitaker was appointed Research Director on July 1, 1935 and he was assisted by a small staff and by a number of expert consultants (as listed in the Report). The report was submitted to the Governor dated January 25, 1937, but a new Act extended the life of the Commission to March 30, 1937. The last meeting minutes bear that date, but the members and the Research Director continued for some months to provide advice and assistance to the Governor and the General Assembly.
Scope and Content
This subgroup consists of the commission's agendas and minutes, reports and study files for each agency, consultants special reports, draft chapters for its report to the General Assembly as outlined in its authorizing legislation, press releases, correspondence, records relating to proposed legislation, and subject files consisting of working papers including correspondence and reference materials.
Related Material
RG 028:001, Commission to Investigate the Advisability of COnsolidating Certain State Boards and Commission and to Investigate the Public Health Laws, 1915.
RG 028:003, Commission to study the Integration of the State Judicial System, 1943-1945.
RG 028:004, Commission on State Government Organization, 1949-1950.
RG 028:005, Commission on Services and Expenditures (Etherington Commission), 1971.
RG 028:006, Committee on the Structure of State Government (Filer Committee), 1975-1977.
RG 028:007, Human Servuces Reorganization Commission, 1977-1979.
RG 028:008, Governor's Study Group on Limitation on Expenditures, 1978-1979.
RG 028:009, Commission to Study the Management of State Government (Thomas Commission), 1989-1991.
RG 028:010, Commission to Effect Government Reorganisation (Hull-Harper Commission), 1991-1992.
Index Terms
Persons:
Hewes, Thomas; Whitaker, Benjamin P
Organizations:
Connecticut. Commission on the Reogranization of State Departments
Subjects:
Administrative agencies -- Connecticut; Executive departments -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Commission on the Reogranization of State Departments -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Politics and government; State governments -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Agendas (administrative records); Correspondence; Memorandums; Minutes; Pamphlets; Press releases; Reports; Statutes
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Acquisition Information
The records of the Commission were e vidently kept in the Budget Division of which Mr. Whitaker was Director for a time, and were transferred to the State Library on August 1, 1944. Earlier, on October 23, 1939, the library received a set of the memoranda and an incomplete set of minuts, minutes from the Hon. Kenneth F. Cramer, a member of the commission. These were bound and catalogued into the "D" collection
Container List
- Records, 1935-1937; 1940-003 (boxes 4-7); 1945-003 (boxes 1-3, 8-22)
  - 1. Meeting minutes, 1935-1937; 3 inches (Box 1)
    Arranged chronologically.
    A complete bound set is available in Government Documents: D q St 293 Mi.
  - 2. Suggested meeting agendas, 1935-1937; 1.5 inches (Box 1)
    Annotated to indicate action taken. Possibly prepared by the Research Director
  - 3. Memoranda, 1935-1937; 4.5 cubic feet
    Includes reports and studies file, containing the initial organization study including powers and duties, personnel and expenditures for each agency as well as consultant's special reports and chapter drafts for the final report. Includes a numerical title list and subkect index in first box.
    Arranged numerically.
    A complete bound set is available in Government Documents: D q St 293 m.
    A hard copy numerical list and "functional index" is available at the History & Genealogy reference desk.
    - 1-26 (Box 2)
    - 27-56 (Box 3)
    - 41-87 (Box 4)
    - 88-110 (Box 5)
    - 111-125 (Box 6)
    - 125A-139 (Box 7)
    - 139A-160 (Box 8)
    - 160A-164, 166-168, 170-173 (Box 9)
    - 174, 176-177. 179-181 (Box 10)
  - 4. Press releases, 1937 January-February; 1 inch (Box 10)
    Mimeographed copies of public release of various parts of the Commission's recommendations.
    Arranged chronologically
  - 5. Correspondence, 1935 June-1937 October; 1.25 cubic feet (Box 2)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent; one folder for each letter of the alphabet with additional folders for principal correspondents (members of the Commission, Governor Cross, consultants).
    - A-C (Box 11)
    - D-C (Box 12)
    - M-S (Box 13)
    - T-Z (Box 14)
  - 6. Proposed legislation, 1937; 8 inches (Box 14-15)
    Drafts, bills, compila6tions, notes and other papers pertaining to legislation proposed by the Commission or growing out of its recommendations.
    Grouped by subject but somewhat disarranged.
  - 7. Subject file, 1935-1937; 2.5 cubic feet
    Working papers and reference materials, including correspondence, memoranda, notes, drafts, pamphlets, reports, etc. pertaining to the functions and organization of state government and the administration of the Commission.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject although some folders are not clearly identified.
    - Advisory committees (Box 16)
    - Aeronatics (Box 16)
    - Agriculture (Box 16)
    - Banking (Box 16)
    - Budge (of Commission) (Box 16)
    - Business regulation (Box 16)
    - Compensation Commission (Box 16)
    - Consultant service (Box 16)
    - Corrections in memoranda (Box 16)
    - Education (Box 17)
    - Executive (Box 17)
    - Finance (Box 17)
    - Industrial relations (Box 17)
    - Judiciary (Box 17)
    - Law enforcement (Box 17)
    - Legislative council (Box 17)
    - Liquor control (Box 17)
    - Military (Box 17)
    - Payrolls (expenditure vouchers) (Box 18)
    - Penology (Box 18)
    - Personnel (Box 18)
    - Personnel (continued) (Box 19)
    - Public health (Box 19)
    - Public utilities (Box 19)
    - Public welfare (Box 19)
    - Public works (Box 20)
    - Purchasing (Box 21)
    - Social Security (Box 21)
    - Social trends (Box 21)
    - State hospitals (Box 22)
    - Unemployment (Box 22)
    - Water agencies (Box 22)
  - 8. Price study worksheets, 1935; 4 inches (Box 22)
  - 9. Examination of status on bonds of State officials, 1936 December 3; .5 inches (Box 22)
    Carbon copy of 72-page report prepared by D.P. O'Connor and submitted to Edward J. Daly, Attorney General.